Register of the Iurii Petrovich Miroliubov Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Iurii Petrovich Miroliubov papers
1928-1990
2000C89
Hoover Institution Archives
10 microfilm reels (1.5 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, correspondence, and printed matter, relating to Russian literature and to Russian émigré affairs.
Miroliubov, IUrii Petrovich, 1892-1970
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
IUrii Miroliubov was born on 30 July 1892 (O.S.) in the town of Bakhmut, Ekaterinoslavskaia guberniia. The First World War interrupted his studies at the University of St. Vladimir in Kiev, and as an officer he served in the White Army in South Russia, evacuating the country in 1920. He resumed his education in Prague and Belgium, where he settled and became a chemical engineer in charge of a glycerin-producing factory.
Miroliubov also wrote prose and poetry, primarily folkloric renderings of ancient Russian history, most of which was published by his widow posthumously in the 1970s-1990s, but which also appeared in contemporary newspapers and journals. In 1954, he acquired the San Francisco-based émigré periodical Zhar-ptitsa, and moved to San Francisco, California, to continue its publication. It is in this journal that the document known as the "Vles-Kniga" (aka "Kniga Velesa", "Vlesova Kniga") first made its appearance. Purporting to be a newly-discovered ancient manuscript describing the history of the Eastern Slavs in pre-Christian times, the existence and dissemination of this literary mystification is due in large measure to Miroliubov's efforts.
Following the closure of Zhar-ptitsa in the late 1950s Miroliubov decided to return to Belgium, but never made it, dying at sea on 6 November 1970.
Chronology
1892 July 30 (O.S.) Born, Bakhmut, Ekaterinoslavskaia guberniia, Russia
1915 Graduated, Kiev University
1921-1924 University student in Prague, Czechoslovakia
1925 Author, Dva svieta
1954 Emigrated to the United States
1970 November 6 Died aboard a ship en route to Europe
1974 Author, Babushkin sunduk (published posthumously)
1977 Author, Prabkino uchenie (published posthumously)
1990 Author, Skazy Zakharikhi (published posthumously)
Scope and Content Note
Iurii Miroliubov was a chemist, journalist, poet and writer with an interest in ancient Russian folklore. He is best known for his attempts to synthesize a new history of pre-historic Russia in a series of books and articles, many of which were based on the forgery known as "Vlesova kniga," which he helped promulgate as editor of the journal Zhar-ptitsa. Materials relating to this forgery can be found among his writings as well as in the subject file. Other materials of interest are his reminiscences of the Russian colony in Belgium during the German occupation (1939-1945), numerous newspaper columns, many of which deal with émigré political and social life in post-World War II Belgium, and short stories, some of which were compiled and published under the titles Babushkin sunduk and Prabkino uchenie.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Belgium.; Russia.; Russian literature.; Russians--Belgium.; Russians--United States.; United States.
- Biographical File, 1928-1972 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Clipping, legal documents, obituary, patents and miscellany, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Correspondence, 1930-1969 (Box 1)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- Speeches and Writings, 1930-1992 (Box 1-7)
  Books, newspaper columns, poetry, reviews, and short stories, arranged chronologically by title
- Zhar-ptitsa File, 1935-1968 (Box 7-8)
  Correspondence and writings (short stories, poetry, non-fiction) submitted for publication in Zhar-ptitsa, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent or author. Includes Miroliubov's editorials written specifically for Zhar-ptitsa
- Subject File, 1926-1983 (Box 8-9)
  Clippings, correspondence, writings, and printed matter, arranged alphabetically by heading
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1928-1972 (Box 1)
  - Bibliography (Folder 1: 1)
  - Clipping about Miroliubov (Folder 1: 2)
  - Legal documents relating to a claim against the city of San Francisco, 1960-1962 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Letters of introduction for Miroliubov (Folder 1: 4)
  - Obituary (Folder 1: 5)
  - Patents. (Folder 1: 6)
    Includes related correspondence
  - Miscellany (Folder 1: 7)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1930-1969
  General note
  See also ZHAR-PTITSA FILE for editorial and other correspondence relating to this periodical
  - General, 1930-1969 (Folder 1: 8)
  - Unidentified, 1952-1968 and undated (Folder 1: 9)
  - Biriuk, A., 1968 (Folder 1: 10)
  - Emmé, E., 1952-1956 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Ghelfand, S., 1952 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Iuzefovich, A. M., 1965-1968 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Kirpich (Kyrpych), A., 1968 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Knirsha, 1953-1956 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Konstantinov, Petr Filaretovich, 1951 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Kur (Kurenkov, Koor), A., 1957-1966 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Makarevich, D., 1952-1953 and undated (Folder 1: 18)
  - Mesniaev, G., 1964-1965 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Platunov, Konstantin Nikolaevich, 1945-1949 (Folder 1: 20)
    See also SUBJECT FILE
  - Poll, Walter, 1957 (Folder 1: 21)
  - Pronin, G., n.d. (Folder 1: 22)
    See also ZHAR-PTITSA FILE
  - Pushkarskii, N. Iu., 1954 (Folder 1: 23)
  - Samoilov, Efim F.
    See ZHAR-PTITSA FILE
  - Savinov, Anna and Sergei, 1944-1967 (Folder 1: 24)
  - Schutte (?), Maya, 1957-1958 (Folder 1: 25)
  - Skripnik, M., 1968 (Folder 1: 26)
  - Soglasiye, 1958 (Folder 1: 27)
  - Solonevich, Boris Luk'ianovich, 1956 (Folder 1: 28)
  - Terapiano, G., 1962-1969 (Folder 1: 29)
  - Turianitsa, M., 1966-1968 (Folder 1: 30)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1930-1992
  See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE/Bibliography. May include writings published in Zhar-ptitsa; for Miroliubov's editorials written specifically for Zhar-ptitsa, see ZHAR-PTITSA FILE/Miroliubov, Iurii Petrovich
  - General
    - General - "Obryvki,"., 1930-1950 (Folder 1: 31)
      Holograph and typescript. This file contains brief articles, stories and fragments of same, letters to the editor, and poetry, filed together by Miroliubov
    - Newspaper columns.
      Holograph, typescript and printed copies
      - Undated (Folder 1: 32)
      - 1947-1954 (Folder 1: 33)
    - Poetry, 1941-1952 and undated (Folder 2: 1)
  - "Antonovskaia roza,", n.d. (Folder 2: 2)
    Typescript
  - "Balandin chebrets," (Folder 2: 3)
  - "Bieloiar-tsviet,", n.d. (Folder 2: 4)
  - "Boevoi soratnik,", n.d. (Folder 2: 5)
  - "Chum-la-la,", n.d. (Folder 2: 6)
  - "Dymok,", n.d. (Folder 2: 7)
  - "Garmalii s Gamaliem,", n.d. (Folder 2: 8)
  - "Geroi F. M. Dostoevskago i revoliutsiia,", n.d. (Folder 2: 9)
  - "Iur'evskiia zvorozhiny,", n.d. (Folder 2: 10)
  - "Kornilovskii udarn. polk v vosemnadtsatom godu,", n.d. (Folder 2: 11)
  - "Lunnyi son,", n.d. (Folder 2: 12)
  - "Mazhary,", n.d. (Folder 2: 13)
  - "Na sundukakh," (Folder 2: 14)
  - "O strategii zheleznodorozhnogo stroitel'stva,", n.d. (Folder 2: 15)
    Holograph
  - "Ob odnoi iuzhno-russkoi poslovitsie,", n.d. (Folder 2: 16)
  - "Ottsovskoe bogatstvo,", n.d. (Folder 2: 17)
  - "Paskha na Libnie,", n.d. (Folder 2: 18)
  - "Pastukh Korniei,", n.d. (Folder 2: 19)
  - "Poniatie 'Gertsog' v Prichernomor'e,", n.d. (Folder 2: 20)
  - "Programma doklada o tekushchem momente i zadachakh natsii,", n.d. (Folder 2: 21)
    Holograph and typescript
  - "Prostota slozhnosti,", n.d. (Folder 2: 22)
  - "Razgovor v avtomobilie,", n.d. (Folder 2: 23)
  - "Razvienchan-li Blok,", n.d. (Folder 2: 24)
  - "Rozhdestvo na Rusi,", n.d. (Folder 2: 25)
  - "Rzhevnitse,", n.d. (Folder 2: 26)
  - "Rzhichany,", n.d. (Folder 2: 27)
  - "Sharaban,", n.d. (Folder 2: 28)
  - "Smert' dieda Kanunnika,", n.d. (Folder 2: 29)
  - "Smiekh,", n.d. (Folder 2: 30)
  - "Staryi traktir v Iukklie,", n.d. (Folder 2: 31)
  - "Tiul'pany,", n.d. (Folder 2: 32)
  - "Trudnyi den',", n.d. (Folder 2: 33)
  - "Tsarskii strazhnik,", n.d. (Folder 2: 34)
  - "Tsvietushchiia iabloni,", n.d. (Folder 2: 35)
  - "U siedogo Kaspiia,", n.d. (Folder 2: 36)
  - "Vied'ma s Klishi,", n.d. (Folder 2: 37)
  - "Vospominaniia o Pragie dvadtsatykh godov,", n.d. (Folder 2: 38)
  - "Zadachi dnia,", n.d. (Folder 2: 39)
  - "Zapiski po metafizikie,", n.d. (Folder 2: 40)
  - "K poznaniiu Rossii,"., 1936 (Folder 2: 41)
    Typescript. Includes holograph postscript dated 1949
  - "Camarade Sypniak," Cité moderne, 1938 (Folder 2: 42)
    Printed copy
  - "Mysli po povodu voennago iskusstva,"., 1942 March 18 (Folder 2: 43)
  - "Beregites',"., 1946 (Folder 2: 44)
  - "Temnaia obiednia,"., 1947 May (Folder 2: 45)
  - "Vtoraia Velikaia voina, g.g. v Bel'gii," Russkaia zhizn', 1940-1945 1947 May - June (Folder 2: 46)
  - "Babushkin sunduk," Russkaia zhizn', 1947 August 23 (Folder 2: 47)
    See also Miroliubov's book of the same title, Babushkin sunduk, 1974, which includes this short story
  - "Kamennyi viek,"., 1947 September (Folder 2: 48)
  - Review of Vekhi, #1, 1948 (Folder 2: 49)
    Typescript. Includes reviewed issue
  - "Poruchik Kolesnikov,"., 1948 January (Folder 2: 50)
  - "Raz"ezd stopiatyi,"., 1948 July (Folder 2: 51)
  - "Nastuplenie fon-Runshtedta,"., 1948 August (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - "Oblaka,"., 1948 November (Folder 3: 2)
  - "Arkhiv: Eskizy,"., 1950 (Folder 3: 3)
  - "Fundamental'naia kritika Marksizma,"., 1950 (Folder 3: 4)
  - "Nepreryvnost',"., 1950 (Folder 3: 5)
  - "Pamiati Aleksandra Bloka,"., 1950 (Folder 3: 6)
  - "Tochka plavleniia i tochka zatverdieniia,"., 1950 (Folder 3: 7)
  - "Vesna,"., 1950 (Folder 3: 8)
  - "Zapiska po distilliatsii organ. veshchestv,"., 1950 (Folder 3: 9)
  - "Zapiski po organicheskoi khimii: Tsiklany,"., 1950 (Folder 3: 10)
  - "Klikun-trava, 1950 January (Folder 3: 11)
  - "Paslen,"., 1950 August (Folder 3: 12)
  - "Stepnaia chaika,"., 1950 August 9 (Folder 3: 13)
    Note and typescript
  - "Rozovoe maslo,"., 1950 November 15 (Folder 3: 14)
  - "Vvedenie v organicheskuiu khimiiu,"., 1950 December 5 (Folder 3: 15)
  - "Na Shimkhanie,"., 1951 (Folder 3: 16)
  - "Trans-ratsional'nyi mir,"., 1951 (Folder 3: 17)
  - "Sharmanshchik-Porfirych,"., 1952 (Folder 3: 18)
  - Translation into Russian of Sebastian Fogelson, "Moisei i ego religiia,"., 1952 (Folder 3: 19)
  - "Tserkva Gospoda Savaofa,"., 1952 August (Folder 3: 20)
  - "Zamietka o trans-ratsional'nom myshlenii,"., 1953 (Folder 3: 21)
  - "Dlinnoe badyl'e,"., 1954 October (Folder 3: 22)
    Typescript and printed copy
  - Translation into Russian of J. M. Chopin, "Révolutions des peuples du Nord,"., 1956 (Folder 3: 23)
  - Reports before the Museum of Russian Culture on a variety of subjects relating to early Russian history, 1969 February-March (Folder 3: 24)
    Includes associated correspondence
  - Babushkin sunduk, 1974
    - Holograph. (Folder 3: 25-26)
      Includes many stories that were not included in the published edition
    - Holograph (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - Typescript. (Folder 4: 2)
    - Printed copy (Folder 4: 3)
    - Reviews (Folder 4: 4)
  - Rodina-mat', 1975
    - Printed copy (Folder 4: 5)
    - Reviews (Folder 4: 6)
  - Prabkino uchenie, 1977
    - Typescript. (Folder 4: 7-8)
      Contains poems and additional short stories that were not included in the published edition
    - Printed copy (Folder 4: 9)
  - Rig-veda i iazychestvo, 1981 (Folder 4: 10-11)
  - Russkaia mifologiia, 1982 (Box 5)
    - Typescript (Folder 5: 1-2)
    - Printed copy (Folder 5: 3)
  - Russkii iazycheskii fol'klor: Ocherki byta i nravov, 1982 (Folder 5: 4-5)
  - Materialy k preistorii russov, 1983 (Folder 5: 6)
  - Slaviano-russkii fol'klor, 1984 (Folder 5: 7)
  - Fol'klor na iuge Rossii, 1985 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Skaz o Sviatoslavie Khorobrie Kniazie Kievskomie, 1986
    - Typescript (Folder 6: 2-4)
    - Printed copy (Folder 6: 5-6)
  - Slaviane v Karpatakh, 1986 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - O kniaze Kie, 1987 (Folder 7: 2)
  - Obrazovanie Kievskoi Rusi, 1988 (Folder 7: 3)
  - Predistoriia Slaviano-russov, 1988 (Folder 7: 4)
  - Dopolnitel'nye materialy k predistorii russov, 1989 (Folder 7: 5)
  - Materialy k istorii kraine-zapadnykh slavian, 1990 (Folder 7: 6)
  - Skazy Zakharikhi, 1990
    - Typescript (incomplete) (Folder 7: 7)
    - Printed copy (Folder 7: 8)
  - Russkii kalendar', 1992 (Folder 7: 9)
- ZHAR-PTITSA FILE, 1935-1968
  Correspondence and writings (short stories, poetry, non-fiction) submitted for publication
  - Unidentified, n.d. (Folder 7: 10)
    Contains items of minor significance, unsigned or initialed only
  - Bashilov, Boris - Writing, "Mif o dekabristakh,", n.d. (Folder 7: 11)
  - Bel'dennikov, S. I. - Writing, "Za pravo i pravdu,"., [1956] (Folder 7: 12)
    Includes letter
  - Chirkov, Nikolai Semenovich - Correspondence, 1951-1955 (Folder 7: 13)
  - Danilovskii, Aleksei - Writing, "Imperator Nikolai Pervyi,"., 1954 November 23 (Folder 7: 14)
  - Dartau, O. - Poem, n.d. (Folder 7: 15)
  - Dem'ianenko, Aleksandr - Poem (Folder 7: 16)
  - Eristov, Georgii - Poetry, n.d. (Folder 7: 17)
  - Gardner, I. G. - Writings
    - "Karulia,", n.d. (Folder 7: 18)
    - "Tri shkoly russkogo khorovogo tserkovnago pieniia,", n.d. (Folder 7: 19)
    - "Ushedshii mir,", n.d. (Folder 7: 20)
    - "Iz istorii russkago tserkovnago pieniia,"., 1956 (Folder 7: 21)
  - Khodatskii, Iurii - Letter,, and poetry, 1956 1949-1955 (Folder 8: 1)
  - Kramarovskii, A. - Letter,, and poetry, 1957 1935-1943 and undated (Folder 8: 2)
  - Mikhnevich, R. - Writings
    - "Konkordiia,", n.d. (Folder 8: 3)
    - "V tiur'me,"., 1954 April (Folder 8: 4)
  - Miroliubov, Iurii Petrovich - Editorials, 1955-1956 (Folder 8: 5)
  - Pronin, G. - Writings.
    See also CORRESPONDENCE (unrelated to Zhar-ptitsa)
    - "Etiudy o nasekomykh,", n.d. (Folder 8: 6)
      Typescript (incomplete)
    - "Po vsenoshchnoi,", n.d. (Folder 8: 7)
  - Puchkova, Evlampiia Fedorovna
    - Correspondence,, including forwarded letters from Bronislava Pogorelova,, Ivan Solonevich,, and Boris Vlasenko, 1953-1957 and undated 1956 1951-1952 1956 (Folder 8: 8)
    - Poetry, n.d. (Folder 8: 9)
  - Samoilov, Efim Fedorovich
    - Correspondence, 1953-1956 (Folder 8: 10)
    - Summaries of his philosophical system (Folder 8: 11)
    - Writings
      - "K poznaniiu vselennoi,"., 1952-1953 (Folder 8: 12)
        Typescript (series of articles)
      - "Nauka i filosofiia,"., 1956 May 14 (Folder 8: 13)
  - Sigida, N. - Untitled writing, 1956 July 27 (Folder 8: 14)
  - Smidovich, S. and T. - Correspondence, 1950-1968 (Folder 8: 15)
  - Sobolev, A.
    - Correspondence, 1953 (Folder 8: 16)
    - Writing, "Vospominaniia o Sibiri, ,", 1908-1909 n.d. (Folder 8: 17)
  - Spasovskii, M. M. - Writing, "O sobornom nachalie Rusi,", n.d. (Folder 8: 18)
  - Taube-Anichkova, S., Baroness
    - Correspondence, 1956 (Folder 8: 19)
    - Writings
      - "Iz zhizni Tsesarevny,", n.d. (Folder 8: 20)
      - Poetry, n.d. (Folder 8: 21)
  - Tomashevskii-Chernyi, Dr. - Writing, "Vengriia Korolevstvo, Vengriia satelit i russkaia emigratsiia,"., 1957 January 1 (Folder 8: 22)
  - University of Minnesota - Correspondence, 1965 (Folder 8: 23)
  - Vel'skaia, M. - Writing, "Serenada braga,", n.d. (Folder 8: 24)
  - Voronkov, N. - Correspondence, 1956, and poetry (Folder 8: 25)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1926-1983
  Clippings, correspondence, writings and printed matter
  - Izenbek, Fedor. (Folder 8: 26-30)
    Includes his writings on art and military topics (lectures on fortification, chemical warfare and tactics) and documents relating to his life and artistic career, including programs of exhibitions
  - Museum of the Russian Cavalry (Folder 9: 1)
  - Pastac, Isaak (Folder 9: 2)
  - Platunov, Konstantin Nikolaevich. (Folder 9: 3)
    See also CORRESPONDENCE
  - Rossiiskii Imperskii Soiuz-Orden (Folder 9: 4)
  - Russians--Belgium (Folder 9: 5)
  - Savinov, Sergei Iakovlevich. (Folder 9: 6)
  - Vlesova Kniga (Folder 9: 7-9)
  - World War, 1939-1945 --Soviet Union (Folder 9: 10)
  - Miscellany (Folder 9: 11)